Alexander Viand

ADDRESS: ETH ZURICH

APPLIED CRYPTOGRAPHY GROUP

CNB H 106

UNIVERSITÄTSTRASSE 6

8902 ZURICH

PHONE: +41 44 632 02 73

EMAIL: ALEXANDER.VIAND@INF.ETHZ.CH

WEBSITE: VIAND.CH

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in useable security and privacy, privacy enhancing technologies, and the interactions between these technologies and society.

In my research, I work with secure computation technologies including Fully Homomorphic Encryption, Secure Multi-Party Computation and Zero-Knowledge Proofs. I am trying to make these techniques more accessible to non-experts by developing new systems, tools and abstractions.

EDUCATION

	ETH Zurich , DOCTORAL STUDENT IN COMPUTER SCIENCE <i>Thesis advisors</i> : Prof. Dr. Kenneth Paterson, Dr. Anwar Hithnawi
SEPTEMBER 2014 - MARCH 2017	ETH Zurich, MASTER OF SCIENCE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Master Thesis: "Privacy-preserving Cloud Computation using FHE"
SEPTEMBER 2011 - SEPTEMBER 2014	ETH Zurich, BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Master Thesis: "Distributed Fail-Safe Monitoring"

WORK EXPERIENCE

	ETH Zurich, Applied Cryptography Group DOCTORAL STUDENT AND RESEARCH ASSISTANT
AUGUST 2021	Intel
- January 2022	RESEARCH INTERNSHIP "FULLY HOMOMORPHIC ENCRYPTION ENGINEER"
2013 - 2016	ETH Zurich, Chair of Information Technology and Education TEACHING ASSISTANT Course: "Theoretical Computer Science"
2014	ETH Zurich, Chair of Programming Methodology TEACHING ASSISTANT Course: "Formal Methods and Functional Programming"
2012 - 2013	Ausbildungs- und Beratungszentrum für Informatikunterricht TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR "PROGRAMMING FOR CHILDREN (LOGO)" COURSES.

PUBLICATIONS

- Alberto Ibarrondo and **Alexander Viand**Pyfhel: Python for Homomorphic Encryption Libraries
 9th Workshop on Encrypted Computing & Applied Homomorphic Cryptography (WAHC '21). Online, November 2021
- TRAVIS MORRISON, BIJEETA PAL, SARAH SCHEFFLER, **Alexander Viand** (alphabetical order)
 PRIVATE OUTSOURCED TRANSLATION FOR MEDICAL DATA
 In "Protecting Privacy through Homomorphic Encryption", K. Lauter, W. Dai, K. Laine, editors, Springer, 2021
- LUKAS BURKHALTER*, NICOLAS KÜCHLER*, **Alexander Viand**, HOSSEIN SHAFAGH, ANWAR HITHNAWI ZEPH: CRYPTOGRAPHIC ENFORCEMENT OF END-TO-END DATA PRIVACY

 15th USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation (OSDI '21). Online, July 2021
- Alexander Viand, PATRICK JATTKE AND ANWAR HITHNAWI SOK: FULLY HOMOMORPHIC ENCRYPTION COMPILERS 42nd IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (SP '21). Online, May 2021
- Lukas Burkhalter, Anwar Hithnawi, **Alexander Viand**, Hossein Shafagh and Sylvia Ratnasamy TimeCrypt: Encrypted Data Stream Processing at Scale with Cryptographic Access Control 17th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI '20). Santa Clara, CA, February 2020.
- Lukas Burkhalter, **Alexander Viand**, Anwar Hithnawi and Hossein Shafagh. Robust Secure Aggregation for Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning with Adversaries Workshop on Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning (PPML '19). London, Great Britain, November 2019
- Alexander Viand and Hossein Shafagh
 Marble: Making Fully Homomorphic Encryption Accessible to All
 6th Workshop on Encrypted Computing & Applied Homomorphic Cryptography (WAHC '18). Toronto, Canada, October 2018

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- REVIEWER | 29th World Wide Web Conference (WWW '20). Tapei, Taiwain, April 2020.
- President | Scientific Staff Association at the Department of Computer Science at ETH Zurich, 2018-2021.

SUPERVISED STUDENTS

- MORITZ WINGER | MSc Thesis "Automated Hybrid Parameter Selection & Circuit Analysis for FHE", 2021.
- FABIO BERTSCHI | BSc Thesis "Private ML as a Service for Natural Language Processing", 2021.
- PATRICK JATTKE | MSc Thesis "Advanced Optimization Strategies for the Marble FHE Compiler", 2020.
- ULLA AESCHBACHER | MSc Thesis "An Accessible High-Level Language for Advanced Cryptography", 2020.
- MARIO STÖCKLI | BSc Thesis "Improving the Marble Fully Homomorphic Encryption Framework", 2019.
- M. NIEDERBERGER | MSc Thesis "Variational Autoencoder KnowledgeTransfer", 2019.
- ALEXANDRE CONNAT | MSc Thesis "Differentially Private Decentralized Machine Learning Framework", 2019.
- PASCAL SCHÄRLI | BSc Project "Re:Versi Move Analysis for Reversi", 2018.

LANGUAGES

GERMAN: Native

ENGLISH: Fluent (ILR Level 4+)